<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Car Finance Genie</title>
	<atom:link href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/</link>
	<description>Car Finance Made Easy</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 10:09:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-GB</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Is It Hard To Get Accepted For Car Finance?</title>
		<link>https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/is-it-hard-to-get-accepted-for-car-finance/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlie Clayton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 09:10:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/?p=6347</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Car finance can be a great way to get the car that you want, and allows you to pay for it over time instead of all at once, widening the available selection of vehicles, and giving you more breathing space when it comes to making your purchase. However, getting approved for financing can be difficult [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/is-it-hard-to-get-accepted-for-car-finance/">Is It Hard To Get Accepted For Car Finance?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Car finance can be a great way to get the car that you want, and allows you to pay for it over time instead of all at once, widening the available selection of vehicles, and giving you more breathing space when it comes to making your purchase. However, getting approved for financing can be difficult if you don’t have the right credit score or history.</p>
<p>Below, we take a closer look at just what it takes to get accepted for car finance, including the potential challenges that you may face. We also consider the best way to overcome these and to increase your chances of a successful application.</p>
<p><strong>What Is Car Finance?</strong></p>
<p>Car finance is an agreement between you and a lender where they agree to lend you money in exchange for ownership of your vehicle. You make payments on this loan until you own the vehicle outright, which means you are responsible for paying off the full amount owed.</p>
<p>This payment plan is known as ‘car finance’ because you are borrowing against the value of your car.</p>
<p>The benefits of car finance include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Flexibility</li>
</ul>
<p>With car finance, you can choose how much you would like to borrow, and when you need to start repaying. This allows you greater choice when it comes to making a selection for your new car, and also enables access to a good range of finance deals.</p>
<ul>
<li>Fast Access To Cash</li>
</ul>
<p>If you need a new car quickly and are struggling to save, then car finance could be the answer. With a quick approval process, you can take advantage of the funds immediately, without having to wait weeks or months for a bank loan.</p>
<ul>
<li>Lower Interest Rates</li>
</ul>
<p>Because you are borrowing against the equity in your car, lenders will often offer <a href="https://www.whatcar.com/advice/buying/is-a-bank-loan-better-than-dealer-car-finance/n18856">lower interest rates</a> than with other forms of personal debt. The average rate for car loans is around 4% per annum, whereas personal loans typically carry higher rates of up to 15%.</p>
<p><strong>How Does Car Finance Work?</strong></p>
<p>To apply for car finance, you must first find a suitable lender who will accept your application.</p>
<p>Once you have found a lender, you will need to complete a simple online form, providing</p>
<p>information about yourself and your financial situation, as well as the car you intend to purchase. If you meet the criteria required by the lender, they will send you a formal letter confirming their acceptance &#8211; in some cases, this may be done by email.</p>
<p>Once you receive this letter, you may be asked to arrange a meeting with the lender to discuss the details of your application; again, this may be done online in some cases. At this stage, you will need to provide proof of income, savings, and any outstanding debts. After this, you will be expected to sign a contract agreeing to repay the loan. Finally, you will need to hand over your car title to the lender, so that they can register the transfer of ownership.</p>
<p>Once the transaction has been completed, you will need to make regular payments to the lender, and keep them informed of any changes to your circumstances.</p>
<p><strong>What Are My Options When Looking For Car Finance?</strong></p>
<p>If you want to buy a car, but can’t afford to purchase it upfront from your own funds, there are several options that might work for you. These include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Personal Loan</li>
</ul>
<p>A personal loan is a type of loan <a href="https://www.moneyhelper.org.uk/en/everyday-money/types-of-credit/personal-loans">that can be obtained from banks and other lenders</a>. It isn’t secured against any asset such as your home or car, which is why these loans are also known as ‘unsecured loans’. However, you will need to demonstrate that you have sufficient funds available to cover the loan, and you will need to pay back the full amount when the term ends.</p>
<ul>
<li>Hire Purchase</li>
</ul>
<p>This is one of the most popular forms of car finance here at Car Finance Genie; it involves fixed monthly payments being made over time, until the end of the loan term. Once those repayments are over, you will automatically become the owner of the car.</p>
<ul>
<li>Personal Contract Purchase</li>
</ul>
<p>This type of car finance has a lot in common with Hire Purchase deals; again, there are fixed monthly payments involved. Where a Personal Contract Purchase (PCP) agreement differs, is that once you have finished the main repayments on the loan, you will need to make a final ‘balloon’ payment in order to acquire the vehicle permanently. However, some drivers do like having the flexibility to walk away from a car at the end of a PCP deal, which also tends to have lower monthly repayments than a Hire Purchase arrangement.</p>
<p><strong>How Can I Improve My Chances of Being Accepted For Car Finance?</strong></p>
<p>There are a number of steps that you can take to boost your chances of being successfully approved for car finance, and these include:</p>
<ol>
<li>Get Pre-Approved Before Applying</li>
</ol>
<p>Before you go ahead and apply for car finance, make sure that you check whether any of the lenders you are considering have pre-approved you for a loan. This way, you won&#8217;t waste time filling out forms and waiting for them to respond to your enquiry.</p>
<ol>
<li>Have Good Credit History</li>
</ol>
<p>When applying for car finance, most lenders will require you to have a minimum credit rating before they will consider your application. In order to qualify for a loan, you will need to show that you can afford to pay back the money borrowed. Lenders use your credit score to help determine whether you are likely to be able to do this.</p>
<p>Your credit score is calculated from three main factors:</p>
<ul>
<li>Payment History</li>
</ul>
<p>This includes all of your previous repayments made towards your current account. Your payment history shows how reliable you are at managing your finances.</p>
<ul>
<li>Credit Limit</li>
</ul>
<p>This is the total amount of money available to you through your credit cards, overdrafts, store cards, and so on.</p>
<ul>
<li>Repayments</li>
</ul>
<p>This factor takes into consideration how much you have paid off on your existing accounts, and how long it took you to clear those balances.</p>
<p>There are a number of ways that you can improve your credit history, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>Making Regular Payments On Time</li>
</ul>
<p>Make sure that you always pay your bills on time. If you miss a payment or fail to make an agreed repayment date, this could negatively affect your credit score.</p>
<ul>
<li>Keeping Track Of All Your Bills</li>
</ul>
<p>It is important to monitor your spending carefully so that you don&#8217;t exceed your budget. Keep track of all your bills and ensure you never miss a payment.</p>
<ul>
<li>If You Have Bad Credit, Start Saving Now</li>
</ul>
<p>If you currently have bad credit and want to get accepted for car finance, you may be best advised to try to improve your credit score first. Once you have done this, you can look for a lender who will accept you even though your credit score isn&#8217;t perfect.</p>
<p>Alternatively, widen your net of potential lenders – <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/bad-credit-car-finance/">bad credit car finance is an option to consider</a> that might help you secure the loan you need.</p>
<ol>
<li>Pay Off Any Debts That Are Holding Back Your Application</li>
</ol>
<p>If there are any debts that you owe, such as unpaid utility bills, bank charges, or other loans, you should try to settle them before you apply for car finance &#8211; these can be seen as a black mark by lenders, and may harm your chances of successfully obtaining car finance.</p>
<ol>
<li>Don&#8217;t Apply With A Low Deposit</li>
</ol>
<p>Lenders usually prefer applicants who offer a higher deposit when they apply for car finance. However, if you&#8217;re struggling to find a suitable vehicle, you might not be able to come up with a large enough deposit.</p>
<ol>
<li>Make Sure You Can Afford The Loan Amount</li>
</ol>
<p>You will need to prove that you can afford to repay the loan. This means showing that you have sufficient income to cover the payments and that you won&#8217;t end up having to sell anything to meet the repayments.</p>
<ol>
<li>Avoid Making Too Many Applications At One Time</li>
</ol>
<p>Applying for multiple loans at once can cause problems because each one of them will appear on your credit report. This can damage your credit rating, which will make it harder for you to obtain car finance in the future.</p>
<ol>
<li>Be Careful When Choosing A Lender</li>
</ol>
<p>When applying for car finance, it&#8217;s important to choose a reputable lender. Look for a company that has been around for a while, and that offers competitive rates.</p>
<p>When selecting your lender, make sure that you read their terms and conditions thoroughly. They should explain what happens if you default on your repayments, and give you information about how to resolve disputes.</p>
<p><strong>Final Thoughts</strong></p>
<p>The best way to get approved for car finance is to follow our tips above. By following these steps, you should be able to avoid making mistakes that could put off potential lenders, and increase your chances of success. For more information, why not get in touch, and see how we could help you fund the purchase of your dream car in no time?</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/is-it-hard-to-get-accepted-for-car-finance/">Is It Hard To Get Accepted For Car Finance?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How long does car finance approval take in the UK?</title>
		<link>https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/how-long-does-car-finance-approval-take-in-the-uk/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlie Clayton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2022 13:07:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/?p=6342</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Amid the intense cost-of-living pressures of the last year or so, it is fair to say that car finance has shown great relevance as a consumer product for many people. With the statistics suggesting that the consumer car finance market recorded 9% growth last year – despite global economic uncertainty and a chip shortage making [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/how-long-does-car-finance-approval-take-in-the-uk/">How long does car finance approval take in the UK?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Amid the intense cost-of-living pressures of the last year or so, it is fair to say that car finance has shown great relevance as a consumer product for many people. With the statistics suggesting that the consumer car finance market <a href="https://uk.motor1.com/news/568054/consumer-car-finance-market-2021/">recorded 9% growth last year</a> – despite global economic uncertainty and a chip shortage making it trickier to get new cars on the forecourt – it is clear that a lot of people are still using a loan to fund a car purchase.</p>
<p>So, what does all that mean for you? Well, it means you might well be reading this as someone who would like to get approved for a car finance deal yourself, and you might not want to be waiting for too long to make it happen. After all, you may need to get on the road in a new vehicle immediately.</p>
<p>This, in turn, brings us onto the subject of the speed of the car finance approval process. There is no doubt that historically, the process of getting one’s signature on a car finance deal wasn’t exactly known for being quick. It seemed to be a situation where stacks of paperwork would inevitably be involved, as paranoid lenders pored over the applicant’s credentials before making a decision on a potential loan.</p>
<p>Fast-forward to the 2020s, and lenders – of course – aren’t exactly less paranoid than they used to be. But with the advancement of digital technology, it has unquestionably become a much faster and less cumbersome process to make an initial application for car finance. That is the case even if you are applying not directly to a lender, but instead to a broker, which might have an extensive network of lenders to call upon.</p>
<p>But it’s one thing to know you can <em>apply </em>for a car finance deal online in a matter of minutes, and it’s quite another thing to know how long the <em>approval</em> will take. So, what <em>do </em>you need to know about the timeframes involved when it comes to this popular consumer product?</p>
<p><strong>There isn’t a single answer to how long car finance approval will take </strong></p>
<p>The short answer to the question of how long it takes to get approved for car finance in the UK is… well, there isn’t a short answer.</p>
<p>In some cases, it might take just seconds to be given a decision, while in other cases, you might be waiting several days. It all hinges on such factors as the specific lender that you approach, the state of your finances, and what type of car you would like to use car finance to purchase.</p>
<p>It’s a similar situation when you apply for car finance through a broker such as Car Finance Genie. It will typically take just a few minutes to complete and submit our online car finance application form, in which you will need to provide us with key details such as the exact amount you would like to borrow, and whether you are looking to finance a car, van, motorbike, or caravan/motorhome.</p>
<p>Once you have submitted your car finance application with us, we will naturally work as fast as we can to give you a decision. You might have a decision from us within minutes, but if not, we will strive to give you a decision on the same day if possible.</p>
<p>One of the reasons why the process is slightly more complicated in our case, is that as <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/">car finance specialists</a>, we are <em>brokers </em>rather than lenders. That means we are not lenders in our own right, but instead represent multiple lenders that are among the most respected in the industry.</p>
<p>When you apply through us, we will compare the deals those lenders can make available in light of the details you supplied in your car finance application. We will then be able to present those deals to you, so that you can select the one that works best for you. From there, you will be able to proceed to final approval, before getting on with choosing that car you’re so excited about.</p>
<p><strong>The difference between pre-approval and final approval </strong></p>
<p>One of the most important things to appreciate about the car finance approval process, is the distinction between pre-approval for a loan, and final approval.</p>
<p>Some lenders out there will be prepared to give you instant pre-approval following the submission of your application. By “instant”, in some cases we mean you could have a decision within seconds; some other lenders, however, might take a few days to pre-approve you. Again, a lot is likely to depend on your circumstances.</p>
<p>An advantage of getting pre-approved for a car loan is that it gives you a means of ‘locking in’ rates with a particular lender you might have your eye on, so that you can then ‘shop around’ and compare deals from elsewhere. After all, at this stage, you won’t have yet completed the final paperwork that would commit you to any particular car finance deal.</p>
<p>If, on the basis of what you have been offered, you are happy to proceed with the given car finance plan, you might then move on to full approval. Again, the timeframe for this process can vary – everything might be sorted within hours, or within days.</p>
<p><strong>Soft credit searches vs hard credit checks </strong></p>
<p>Whatever the process of applying for and getting approved for car finance ends up looking like for you, it is also important to be aware at all times whether a soft credit check or a hard credit check is required.</p>
<p>Of course, if you’re applying for a loan such as car finance, a credit check – also known as a ‘credit search’ – will need to happen at <em>some</em> point. But as the respective terms suggest, a ‘soft’ credit check is less intrusive than a hard one, simply taking the form of an initial look at some of the information on your credit report, without any other companies being told of this. A soft credit check therefore won’t impact on your credit score.</p>
<p>There is a stark difference between this and a <em>hard </em>credit check, which represents a complete look at your credit report, and will be recorded on your report for other companies to see.</p>
<p>While a hard credit check is a standard part of the process of applying for a loan, a succession of hard credit checks being performed on your report in a relatively short space of time is likely to cause your credit score to go down, at least temporarily. This, in turn, could impact on your ability to obtain credit in the future.</p>
<p>We’re very aware of this distinction here at Car Finance Genie. It’s why, when you apply for car finance using our site, we will only carry out a soft search, and will not perform a hard credit check without your permission.</p>
<p>Hopefully, this can be a reminder for you that speed of approval is far from the <em>only </em>factor you should be concerning yourself with when you are on the lookout for car finance.</p>
<p><strong>How can I speed up the process of getting approved for car finance? </strong></p>
<p>While there are no guarantees in life – and the same certainly applies to how quickly you can get the go-ahead for car finance – taking the following steps should help ensure you get approved for car finance in a shorter space of time.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Make sure you have a good idea of your budget </strong></li>
</ul>
<p>There’s a good reason why the websites of the leading car finance specialists also often have a <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/car-finance-calculator/">car finance calculator</a> available for people to use; you can expect a quicker response to your car finance application if you are realistic with the size of the loan that you request in the first place.</p>
<p>So, we would certainly advise you to carefully consider what your budget is, and how far that budget will go, before you submit any formal car finance application.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Improve your credit score as much as you can </strong></li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/what-credit-score-is-needed-for-car-finance-in-the-uk/">As we have previously written about here at Car Finance Genie</a>, a poor credit score can be a key factor preventing you from getting approved for car finance at all – and even if you are offered a loan, it might be a factor that means it takes longer for your application to be considered.</p>
<p>So, if you have the luxury of taking a bit longer to <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/3-simple-ways-to-increase-your-credit-score/">improve your credit score</a> before you apply for car finance, this could be well worth doing as a means of speeding up your eventual application – and maximising the likelihood of a positive decision.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Have all the necessary documents ready </strong></li>
</ul>
<p>Making sure you have all the documents to hand that can be crucial to a car finance application – such as your driving licence, bank statements, and proof of employment and income – <em>before </em>you proceed with the actual application, can also help make the process a fast one.</p>
<p>To minimise the chances of delays, you might go as far as scanning the documents into your computer ahead of the application, in addition to keeping physical copies on hand in case they are needed.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Apply early in the morning </strong></li>
</ul>
<p>While some lenders offer ‘same-day approval’, this probably won’t be the case if you apply after the end of business hours on the given day, or at the weekend.</p>
<p>By contrast, applying as early in the day as possible on a weekday, can help ensure your application is attended to rapidly, so that you can have that all-important decision much sooner – hopefully, on the very same day.</p>
<p>There you have it! Hopefully, this article will have given you a helpful rundown of what to expect when it comes to car finance application and approval timescales, so that you can be thorough in your preparations, and realistic in your expectations.</p>
<p><a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/apply/">Get your free, no-obligation application in</a> to the Car Finance Genie team today, and we will work quickly to hopefully bring you the deal that represents the best possible match to your budget and practical requirements. Good luck!</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/how-long-does-car-finance-approval-take-in-the-uk/">How long does car finance approval take in the UK?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Can you get car finance without a license?</title>
		<link>https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/can-you-get-car-finance-without-a-license/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlie Clayton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 11:28:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/?p=6261</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Obtaining one’s driving licence is practically a rite of passage in the UK; for many people, it doesn’t just represent a step into the right to drive a car legally, but also into wider adulthood. Indeed, it is possible to apply for a provisional driving licence from as young as 15 years and nine months [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/can-you-get-car-finance-without-a-license/">Can you get car finance without a license?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Obtaining one’s driving licence is practically a rite of passage in the UK; for many people, it doesn’t just represent a step into the right to drive a car legally, but also into wider adulthood. Indeed, it is possible to apply for a provisional driving licence <a href="https://www.gov.uk/apply-first-provisional-driving-licence">from as young as 15 years and nine months old</a>.</p>
<p>But of course, here at Car Finance Genie, we also realise that many of you reading this might be much older than that, and might simply have ‘not got round’ to applying for a driving licence until a much later stage of life. Maybe you’re in your twenties, thirties, or older, and simply didn’t <em>need </em>to get a driving licence until a change in your personal or professional circumstances?</p>
<p>Whatever the situation, we recognise that a lot of you out there might be in a position where you are seeking to get approved for car finance in order to buy a car, even if you don’t actually have a licence yet. So, is it possible to apply for and be granted car finance even if you lack a driving licence, and what else do you need to know on this subject?</p>
<p><strong>Technically, yes, you can get car finance without a licence </strong></p>
<p>To answer the question posed by this blog article in just a sentence: yes, it is absolutely possible to be approved for car finance if you don’t have a licence yet.</p>
<p>But the question of whether you are <em>likely </em>to be successful with an application for car finance if you don’t presently have a licence… well, that’s a very different matter. Yes, <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/">car finance is available for people without a licence</a> – including potentially from the lenders that we represent here at Car Finance Genie – but most lenders out there will still expect you to have a full driving licence when you apply for car finance.</p>
<p>The reasons for that are simple; it provides proof of your identity as an applicant, and gives the lender reassurance that you are actually legally allowed to drive.</p>
<p><strong>Why would you <em>want </em>car finance if you don’t have a licence, anyway? </strong></p>
<p>This is a question that some of you reading this may understandably have. After all, you might reason, the whole point of car finance is to give you a means of buying a car, and if you aren’t even legally entitled to <em>drive</em> a car yet, why would you want to do that?</p>
<p>But of course, it’s important to acknowledge that ‘life happens’, and people’s circumstances and requirements can change in a very short space of time.</p>
<p>You might not have needed to drive a car in your life so far, but maybe you’re about to get a job where you won’t be able to depend solely on public transport in order to get to your place of work, or perhaps you’re even about to welcome a new addition to the family? In such circumstances, having a car can quickly go from “nice-to-have” to “essential”. You may therefore be looking to obtain your licence, car, <em>and </em>the associated car finance as soon as possible.</p>
<p>Then, there’s the possibility that you might already have a provisional licence, and may have taken a fair few driving lessons already. Maybe you’ve fallen in love with a particular car and would really like to own one in preparation for passing your test, or perhaps you like the idea of buying a car while you are still on your provisional licence, so that you can practise in your own car while being supervised by a suitably qualified passenger?</p>
<p>On the latter point, <a href="https://www.gov.uk/driving-lessons-learning-to-drive/practising-with-family-or-friends">the GOV.UK website provides more information</a>. But basically, you can have a friend or family member supervise you while you drive, as long as they are over 21 years of old, are qualified to drive the type of vehicle you wish to learn in, and have had their full driving licence for a minimum of three years. The supervisor’s driving licence must come from the UK, the EU, Switzerland, Norway, Iceland, or Liechtenstein.</p>
<p>Anyway, you hopefully get the idea. The point we’re making, is that there are circumstances in which someone might conceivably wish to apply for car finance even if they are only presently on a provisional licence, or don’t have a licence at all.</p>
<p><strong>Do people without a full driving licence have much chance of getting approved for car finance? </strong></p>
<p>As we set out above, it can definitely be <em>difficult </em>to secure car finance if you don’t yet have a licence; however, it’s not <em>impossible</em>. There are some lenders out there that do make available car loans to people who don’t have a full licence at the time of their application.</p>
<p>However, it’s important to understand why lenders tend to hesitate to approve the applications of people who lack a full driving licence. They will want to be reassured that you have a genuine reason for wishing to take out the loan in the first place, and if you are a young driver, you might also have little or no credit history. This would make you a riskier person to lend to in the eyes of lenders, as it would be a lot more difficult for them to be confident that you will pay back the money.</p>
<p><strong>How can you boost your chances of obtaining car finance? </strong></p>
<p>Applying to Car Finance Genie for car finance could be one powerful move to increase your chances of being accepted for a loan. This is because we very much build our services around helping people who might have been rejected for car finance by other lenders. We maintain an extensive panel of lenders, and some of these may be able to offer you a car finance quote even if you don’t presently have a full driver’s licence.</p>
<p>However, there are further steps that you might take to bolster your attractiveness to would-be lenders. We’ve written previously on what some of those steps could be, <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/how-to-increase-your-chances-of-getting-finance/">such as working to improve your credit score</a>. You could also increase your chances of a successful car finance application by:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Agreeing to have a guarantor</strong>. A guarantor is a third party – typically a trusted friend or relative – who, as part of your car finance application, might agree to step in to make repayments on your loan if you find yourself unable to do so. As we stated above, a lot of people without a driving licence are young people who lack a credit history, so this move alone could do a lot to reassure a potential lender when they are considering your application.</li>
<li><strong>Applying for joint car finance</strong>. As the term suggests, joint car finance entails having two people on one car finance deal. The potential relevance of this if you don’t have a driving licence is that making a joint application with someone who holds a full driving licence could strengthen your application overall. Again, it can be a way of reassuring a would-be lender. However, joint liability for the deal also means that in the event of you failing to keep up with repayments, both of your credit scores would be adversely impacted.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Could age also affect your prospects when you apply for car finance? </strong></p>
<p>Not all the factors affecting your ability to get approved for car finance will necessarily be ones you can easily help. While, for example, we mentioned above that you can apply for a provisional driving licence before your 16<sup>th</sup> birthday, you won’t be eligible to apply for any kind of credit – such as car finance – until you turn 18.</p>
<p>Age, then, might turn out to be your biggest barrier to accessing car finance, especially given that some lenders set the minimum age requirement at 21.</p>
<p>Other than simply waiting to reach an eligible age before applying for car finance, there isn’t much you can do to get around this. Lenders are simply very nervous about extending credit to people who have little or no credit history, and if you also lack a regular income – as is often the case for young people – an already-tough task of getting car finance will be made even harder.</p>
<p><strong>Allow our team at Car Finance Genie to set out your options </strong></p>
<p>Nothing can be guaranteed when it comes to trying to obtain credit, and we can’t say in this blog post that we will <em>definitely </em>be able to arrange car finance for you if you don’t have a licence.</p>
<p>However, as a well-respected broker here at Car Finance Genie, we have an excellent track record of achieving acceptance for car finance for people who may have been turned down for a loan elsewhere. This includes people who might have lacked a full driving licence at the time of their application.</p>
<p>To learn more about how we might be able to assist you, why not give us a call today, on 01277 583 046? It is also possible to <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/apply/">apply online for car finance from us in minutes</a>, with no obligation to accept whatever quote we present to you. We wish you the best of luck in your pursuit of the best possible car finance deal for your needs!</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/can-you-get-car-finance-without-a-license/">Can you get car finance without a license?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to check whether a car has outstanding finance</title>
		<link>https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/how-to-check-whether-a-car-has-outstanding-finance/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlie Clayton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 11:28:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/?p=6256</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The statistics continue to tell their own story about the popularity and relevance of car finance; as of 2022, some 92% of new private car sales are purchased through new car finance agreements. However, what this means is that at any one time, a given car is very likely to have a car finance deal [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/how-to-check-whether-a-car-has-outstanding-finance/">How to check whether a car has outstanding finance</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The statistics continue to tell their own story about the popularity and relevance of car finance; as of 2022, <a href="https://store.mintel.com/report/uk-car-finance-market-report">some 92% of new private car sales are purchased through new car finance agreements</a>.</p>
<p>However, what this means is that at any one time, a given car is very likely to have a car finance deal attached to it, with the associated responsibilities for the person who took out the agreement. That, in turn, could have significant implications for the potential sale of that car to anyone else.</p>
<p>As they say, “life happens”, and that’s definitely the case when it comes to finance and cars. You might need to buy a car, but you may be anxious to ensure there isn’t any outstanding finance on it when you do – as indeed, you <em>should </em>be alert about. Or you might be the one with a car that you are looking to sell, but which has outstanding finance associated with it.</p>
<p>In situations like the above, what courses of action should you take – and above all else, how can you be sure that a given vehicle does, or doesn’t, have outstanding finance? Below, we’ll answer all these questions.</p>
<p><strong>What is meant by ‘outstanding finance’ on a car? </strong></p>
<p>When sites like ours talk about a car having “outstanding finance” on it, what we’re referring to is a situation where a person has bought a car on finance, but they haven’t yet completed all the payments necessary in order to complete the loan term and acquire the vehicle for good.</p>
<p>It is important to appreciate that when you commit to the kind of car finance that a broker like Car Finance Genie typically offers – in other words, hire purchase (HP) or personal contract purchase (PCP) finance – the car won’t initially be legally <em>yours</em>. Instead, the vehicle will legally belong to the lender, until you have completed all the necessary payments in line with the terms of the deal.</p>
<p>A car finance deal, after all, involves someone borrowing money from a lender to enable them to pay for a car. Such an agreement typically involves an initial deposit being paid, followed by fixed monthly payments until all the money owed has been paid off.</p>
<p>Until the driver has completed all such payments on their own car finance deal – in other words, ‘settled’ the loan – the car will be said to still have outstanding finance.</p>
<p><strong>So, is it illegal to sell a car with outstanding finance? </strong></p>
<p>The short, simple, and ‘safe’ answer to this question is: yes, it is illegal. Indeed, this is the answer you will be widely given if you Google this very question and peruse the various other articles out there on cars with outstanding finance.</p>
<p>The principle of this is very simple: if a given driver is driving a car on a PCP or HP deal as we described above, and there are still payments to be made on the loan before it will be considered settled, they will not have the right to sell the car, because the car won’t yet be theirs to sell.</p>
<p>So, if the driver in this situation <em>did </em>try to sell a car that is still on an active PCP or HP agreement, they would be risking serious legal consequences, including prosecution for fraud, and potential imprisonment.</p>
<p>Now, if you’re sensing a looming “but”, you’re right. You see, the situation is different for those who purchase a car with a personal loan. In this situation, there isn’t any direct connection between the car and the loan, with the person taking out the loan simply using the money borrowed to buy the car outright.</p>
<p>This means they would be entitled to sell the car even in the event of there still being money left on the loan for them to pay off. Of course, in this situation, selling the car would not affect the loan; the debt would still need to be repaid.</p>
<p><strong>Is there a legal way of selling a car with outstanding finance? </strong></p>
<p>Presuming it’s a HP or PCP deal that the given motorist has on their car, and they didn’t use a personal loan to fund their purchase, if they wish to sell the vehicle, they will need to first settle the agreement in some way in order to stay on the right side of the law when selling the car.</p>
<p>The first thing that such a motorist should do, is check the paperwork on their finance deal. This should set out terms that will need to be complied with if the driver wishes to settle the deal – for example, by paying off the balance early.</p>
<p>Another common way of selling a car with outstanding finance, is selling it to a car dealership. What typically happens in this situation is that the dealer agrees to settle the car finance as part of their purchase, with the motorist then being paid any difference.</p>
<p>Of course, in the above scenario, it might turn out that the driver owes more than the car’s value – in which case, the dealer will usually let them know of this shortfall. The motorist will then need to make up the difference before proceeding with the sale or trade-in process.</p>
<p><strong>What are your options for checking whether a car has outstanding finance? </strong></p>
<p>There are a few possibilities; perhaps the most obvious one, particularly if you are interested in buying a particular car from a private individual rather than from a dealer, is to use one of the services out there that are dedicated to checking a car’s history.</p>
<p>These checks are typically referred to as ‘HPI checks’, in a nod to the company that is especially well-known for offering them. However, there are various companies around these days that can carry out such checks.</p>
<p>The emphasis is on checking a range of aspects of a car’s history and status – such as its insurance write-off status, MOT history, and whether the given vehicle has outstanding finance – to help you avoid any nasty surprises.</p>
<p>Services like this also tend to look into such aspects of a vehicle as the number of previous owners DVLA has listed for it, and whether it has previously had a personalised number plate.</p>
<p>As far as dealers are concerned, they usually undertake their own HPI checks of cars before agreeing to take them into their stock, so if you’re buying a car through this route, you should have reasonable confidence that it won’t have outstanding finance attached to it. But we would still recommend you specifically asking the given dealer whether they do this, just to be sure.</p>
<p>As we said above, though, it’s when you are buying from a private individual that you are likely to need to be especially vigilant. While it’s free to <a href="https://www.gov.uk/check-mot-history">check the MOT history of a vehicle via GOV.UK</a>, this service won’t tell you whether the car has outstanding finance, or indeed has been stolen.</p>
<p>There’s something else we feel important to point out if you’re looking to buy from a private owner: it can sometimes take a few working days for the relevant systems maintaining information on outstanding car finance to update themselves, in the event that the car finance has recently been settled.</p>
<p>So, if a seller tells you that the settlement amount has just been paid but this isn’t yet reflected in the result of the HPI check, don’t presume they must be lying. You might therefore be well-advised to take your time in ordering the HPI check before you finally agree to buy the car.</p>
<p><strong>What should I do if I buy a car that turns out to have outstanding finance on it? </strong></p>
<p>As we stated above, there might be a few days’ wait until the payment of the settlement amount on a car finance deal is reflected in the result that a HPI check produces on the relevant vehicle.</p>
<p>However, it can be tricky in these circumstances to determine the truth of the situation, without at least allowing a few days to pass. You should get in touch with the dealer or person who sold you the car as soon as possible, and they ought to be able to clarify the situation for you.</p>
<p>If this doesn’t put your mind at rest, it might be worth reaching out to the company with which you checked the car’s history, to ascertain whether the records might have just been updated.</p>
<p>In the event that you really do end up buying a car that has outstanding payments on it, you might be entitled to keep it, if you are able to prove that you bought the vehicle in good faith, with no knowledge of the outstanding finance.</p>
<p>In the above situation, the car finance provider will carry out its own investigations to determine whether you are an innocent party, and so that it can decide who will need to pay the outstanding finance.</p>
<p>Although there’s a good chance that the person who took out the original car finance agreement will be the one who is expected to pay the outstanding finance, it’s not impossible that the car finance company will instead consider you liable for the remaining amount. If that’s the case for you, it could be a good idea to seek legal advice or to reach out to the <a href="https://www.financial-ombudsman.org.uk/">Financial Ombudsman Service</a>.</p>
<p>Here at Car Finance Genie, we specialise in providing <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/essex/">car finance perfect for people in Essex</a> and around the UK, through our panel of industry-leading lenders. Whatever your needs and expectations may be from your next car, please don’t hesitate to <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/apply/">turn to us for a competitive tailored car finance deal</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/how-to-check-whether-a-car-has-outstanding-finance/">How to check whether a car has outstanding finance</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is it easy to get car finance?</title>
		<link>https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/is-it-easy-to-get-car-finance/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlie Clayton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2022 16:08:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/?p=6030</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Car finance is an innovation that has become increasingly popular in recent years, and it offers a great opportunity for car owners to get their hands on their dream vehicle, even if their budget is a little low. The right car finance allows you to spread your payments, enjoy greater flexibility over your purchase, and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/is-it-easy-to-get-car-finance/">Is it easy to get car finance?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Car finance is an innovation that has become increasingly popular in recent years, and it offers a great opportunity for car owners to get their hands on their dream vehicle, even if their budget is a little low. The right car finance allows you to spread your payments, enjoy greater flexibility over your purchase, and get behind the wheel of your dream new car in next to no time.</p>
<p>You may be wondering, however, just how easy it is to get car finance, and whether you are likely to be successful in your application?</p>
<p>Below, we take a closer look at the essentials of car finance, including the steps you can take to boost your chances of a successful application, and securing your perfect car.</p>
<p><strong>What is car finance?</strong></p>
<p>Car finance simply entails borrowing money from a bank or another financial institution to pay for a car. You will usually need to provide them with some form of security, such as a car title, which they can hold until you have paid back all of the money borrowed. Once this is done, you will then own the car outright, but until the final payment has been made, the lender reserves the right to take the car back.</p>
<p>The process of getting car finance is very similar to applying for any other type of loan – you will fill out a simple online form, providing details about yourself and your current situation, and answer questions regarding your credit history. This information is then sent to one of many lenders who specialise in offering car loans, and once you receive a response, you will be asked to complete a short questionnaire before being given a quote for your desired car.</p>
<p>The main difference between car finance and other types of lending is that in many cases you do not actually make a down payment when you apply for car finance – though it is possible to make a larger initial payment to reduce the monthly payments for the duration of your loan.</p>
<p>In many cases, the value of the car itself is used as collateral, meaning that the amount you borrow is based on its estimated market value. If you decide to sell the car later, you will still owe the same amount as you did when you bought it, so you could end up losing more than you would have, had you taken out a traditional loan. You will also need to continue making payments until the loan is paid off, regardless of whether you sell the car or not.</p>
<p><strong>How much can I borrow?</strong></p>
<p>Once you have received a quote from a lender, you will be able to choose what kind of car you want to buy, and how much you wish to borrow. There are two main options available:</p>
<ul>
<li>A secured loan is where you agree to give the lender a lien against the car&#8217;s title, allowing them to repossess it if you fail to repay the loan.</li>
<li>An unsecured loan does not require you to give the lender a security interest in the car, meaning that you can keep the car if you cannot afford to repay the loan. However, if you default on the loan, the lender can repossess the car without having to go through legal proceedings.</li>
</ul>
<p>While there is theoretically no limit on how much you can borrow, the size of your monthly repayment will depend on the amount you have borrowed, the length of your loan term, and the rate of interest charged by the lender.</p>
<p><strong>Is it easy to get car finance?</strong></p>
<p>When you apply for car finance, you will usually be required to provide some personal details about yourself, including your name, address, date of birth, occupation, income and savings. You will also be asked to provide proof of identity, such as a passport or driving licence.</p>
<p>You will also be asked to state your reasons for wanting to take out a loan, and your financial situation. For example, you might say that you are planning to use the car as a second or third hand purchase, or that you plan to use the car as part of your business. If you are borrowing a large sum of money, you may be asked to provide information about any existing loans or credit cards.</p>
<p>The lender will then look at all this information, along with the car&#8217;s condition and history, to assess whether they think they can lend you the money you need. They will compare the value of the car with the amount you have borrowed and work out what their maximum lending limit is.</p>
<p>The lender will then present you with a number of different quotes, depending on the type of loan you request. These include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Fixed rate</li>
</ul>
<p>A <a href="https://www.thebalance.com/fixed-rate-loans-315603">fixed rate loan</a> offers a set payment each month, regardless of how much you owe. While this makes it easy to budget, it may mean that you miss out on potential savings if rates fall over the course of the loan term.</p>
<ul>
<li>Variable rate</li>
</ul>
<p>With a variable rate loan, the lender sets the interest rate each month based on market conditions. This gives you more flexibility when it comes to managing your finances, but you may end up paying more in the long run because the rate rises over the life of the loan.</p>
<ul>
<li>Interest only</li>
</ul>
<p>An interest only loan allows you to make payments while the balance remains low. Once the loan has been paid off, you will still own the car.</p>
<ul>
<li>Personal contract hire</li>
</ul>
<p>With a PCH loan, you agree to pay back the full amount of the loan within a specified time frame. After this point, you will become the owner of the car.</p>
<p>If you decide to accept one of the offers, you will need to sign a contract agreeing to repay the money. You will also be given a repayment schedule, detailing exactly when you must start making payments.</p>
<p>Once you&#8217;ve accepted a quote from a lender, you will be sent a formal application form. You will usually need to complete this before you can proceed with the process. The application form will ask you to confirm certain details, including your name, contact telephone numbers, email addresses, employment status and current salary.</p>
<p>Once you&#8217;ve completed the form, you&#8217;ll need to send copies of the following documents to the lender:</p>
<ul>
<li>Proof of ID</li>
</ul>
<p>A copy of your passport or driving licence.</p>
<ul>
<li>Proof of income</li>
</ul>
<p>Your most recent payslip (pay slip) showing your gross monthly earnings.</p>
<ul>
<li>Proof of savings</li>
</ul>
<p>A bank statement showing your average monthly savings.</p>
<ul>
<li>Proof of equity</li>
</ul>
<p>A valuation certificate stating the vehicle&#8217;s current value.</p>
<p>In addition, lenders may require you to submit other documentation, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Vehicle history report</li>
</ul>
<p>This report shows the car&#8217;s previous owners and its mileage. Lenders may also want to see an MOT certificate and log book if you are purchasing your loan separately to the vehicle in question.</p>
<ul>
<li>Car valuation certificate</li>
</ul>
<p>This document states the car&#8217;s worth and helps lenders determine whether they can offer you a competitive deal. If you&#8217;re buying the car for cash, you should get a valuation done by a professional valuer.</p>
<ul>
<li>Proof of insurance</li>
</ul>
<p>You will also need to provide proof of insurance cover. This could take the form of a policy issued by your insurer, or a letter confirming that your existing policy covers the car.</p>
<p>The last thing you need to do is check that all the information provided is correct. Make sure that everything matches what was written down on the application form. If there are any discrepancies, the lender will let you know about them during the next stage of the process.</p>
<p><strong>The application process</strong></p>
<p>Once you have submitted all the required paperwork, you&#8217;ll receive a response letting you know whether the lender is interested in taking your application further.</p>
<p>If you are lucky enough to receive a positive reply, you&#8217;ll then move on to the second stage of the process. At this point, you might be asked to attend an appointment at the lender&#8217;s office. During this meeting, you&#8217;ll be able to discuss the terms of the finance agreement and finalise the details of how much you&#8217;ll need to borrow.</p>
<p>At the end of the meeting, you may need to give the lender a <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/car-finance-with-no-deposit/">deposit</a>. This acts as security against any problems that might arise later on. For example, if you default on your repayments, the lender can repossess your car and keep the deposit. In some cases, the deposit acts as a downpayment and can reduce your monthly repayment.</p>
<p><strong>Final thoughts</strong></p>
<p>Car finance can be a great way to help you get your hands on your dream car – but this isn&#8217;t something to be entered into lightly.</p>
<p>It is important that you have all the facts to hand, and that you have double-checked you are able to meet your financial obligations each month for the life of the loan.</p>
<p>So, now that you know a little something about what’s involved in seeking and obtaining car finance… why not <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/apply/">apply today to discover what car you could get your hands on</a>?</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/is-it-easy-to-get-car-finance/">Is it easy to get car finance?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How does online car finance work?</title>
		<link>https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/how-does-online-car-finance-work/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlie Clayton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2022 16:06:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/?p=6027</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Buying a new car is an exciting prospect – but also one that can be more than a little pricey. Many car owners are turning to online car financing when it comes to upgrading their motor, and this can increase the range of choices that you have, as well as allow you to enjoy more [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/how-does-online-car-finance-work/">How does online car finance work?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Buying a new car is an exciting prospect – but also one that can be more than a little pricey. Many car owners are turning to online car financing when it comes to upgrading their motor, and this can increase the range of choices that you have, as well as allow you to enjoy more car for your</p>
<p>money, even if your budget is a little low.</p>
<p>But just what is online <a href="/bad-credit-car-finance/">car finance</a>, and how does it work in reality? We took a closer look.</p>
<p><strong>What is online car finance?</strong></p>
<p>Online car finance is a way of buying a car that has been financed by a bank or another lending institution. It&#8217;s often referred to as &#8220;car finance&#8221;, but there are actually two different types: secured and unsecured. In both cases, you will need to take out a loan from a financial institution to cover the cost of the vehicle. The difference between them lies in the type of security that they offer.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nerdwallet.com/uk/secured-loans/what-is-a-secured-loan-and-is-it-the-right-option-for-me/">Secured loans</a> come with a lien on the car, meaning that the lender has a claim over the vehicle until the full amount is paid back. This means that if you don&#8217;t pay back the entire sum within the agreed time frame, then the bank can repossess the car and sell it at auction.</p>
<p>Secured loans tend to be cheaper than unsecured ones because they&#8217;re less likely to go into default. However, they do mean that you&#8217;ll have to hand over the title of the car to the lender, so you should make sure you understand exactly what you&#8217;re getting yourself into before signing up!</p>
<p>Unsecured loans are much easier to get hold of, as they don&#8217;t require any form of collateral. Instead, they rely on credit history and income levels to determine whether you qualify for a loan. If you&#8217;ve got a good track record with lenders, then you should find that you can secure a lower interest rate than you would with a secured loan.</p>
<p>But remember, the higher your debt-to-income ratio (the total amount of money that you owe compared to your monthly disposable income), the more risk that the lender takes. So, if you&#8217;re struggling to keep up with repayments, you might want to think about taking out a secured loan instead.</p>
<p><strong>What are the advantages of online car finance?</strong></p>
<p>There are plenty of advantages to using online car finance, and some of the main ones include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Speedier process</li>
</ul>
<p>Securing online car finance is usually quicker than going through a traditional dealership. You won&#8217;t need to wait around for weeks while your application is processed, and you shouldn&#8217;t have to spend hours filling out lengthy forms either.</p>
<ul>
<li>More choices</li>
</ul>
<p>When you use online car finance, you can access a wide variety of cars and models. There are many factors that will likely influence which model you end up choosing, including price, mileage, safety ratings and fuel consumption.</p>
<ul>
<li>Lower interest rates</li>
</ul>
<p>The interest rates that you&#8217;ll be charged for online car finance can be significantly lower than those offered by traditional dealerships. This is partly due to the fact that banks aren&#8217;t making a profit when they lend money to customers, so they pass these savings onto you.</p>
<ul>
<li>Flexibility</li>
</ul>
<p>The flexibility provided by online car finance allows you to buy whatever car you like, whenever you like: provided that you successfully pass the credit check or have the collateral to put down for a secured loan, you will have far more freedom to choose your dream car.</p>
<p><strong>What is a credit check?</strong></p>
<p>A credit check is a process used by lenders to assess your ability to repay a loan. The information gathered during this process includes things such as your employment status, current salary, and your credit rating.</p>
<p><strong>How can I increase my chances of passing a credit check?</strong></p>
<p>A credit check is a necessary part of the car finance process, but it doesn&#8217;t necessarily have to be a negative one. Many people believe that having a poor credit score will prevent them from securing a loan, but in reality, most lenders will overlook a bad credit rating if you provide an explanation for why you had problems paying off previous debts.</p>
<p>There are a number of things you can do to improve your credit score, and these include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Pay your bills on time</li>
</ul>
<p>If you regularly pay your bills late, it&#8217;s likely that your credit rating will suffer. In order to avoid getting into this situation, make sure that you always pay your bills on time.</p>
<ul>
<li>Keep your balance low</li>
</ul>
<p>It&#8217;s important to try and keep your outstanding balances below 30% of your available credit limit. This way, you&#8217;re not putting yourself at too great a risk of incurring additional fees.</p>
<ul>
<li>Don&#8217;t take out too much debt</li>
</ul>
<p>It may seem tempting to take out a large loan in order to purchase a new car, but doing so could actually damage your credit rating. Instead, look for smaller amounts of cash that you can afford to repay over time.</p>
<ul>
<li>Use an app to monitor your spending</li>
</ul>
<p>One of the best ways to ensure that you don&#8217;t get into debt is to monitor how much you&#8217;re spending each month. If you find that you&#8217;re spending more than you earn, you should start looking for ways to cut back on unnecessary expenses.</p>
<p>You might consider cutting down on eating out, shopping trips and entertainment, or even selling items that you no longer want. Whatever you decide to do, it&#8217;s important to stick with it until you&#8217;ve managed to reduce your expenditure by around 20%.</p>
<p>You can also set up an automatic payment system through your bank account. By setting up regular payments, you won&#8217;t need to worry about missing any payments.</p>
<ul>
<li>Make sure your debts are paid off</li>
</ul>
<p>Another important element in boosting your credit score is to pay off any outstanding debts that you have. It&#8217;s worth noting that some types of debt, such as payday loans, are considered unsecured loans, which means that they don&#8217;t count towards your overall credit score.</p>
<p>However, other types of debt, including student loans and mortgages, are considered secured loans. These are counted towards your credit rating, so it makes sense to work hard to pay them off as soon as possible.</p>
<ul>
<li>Consider securing a loan with a lower interest rate</li>
</ul>
<p>Many people choose to secure their loans using a personal guarantee, which means that they&#8217;ll be responsible for repaying the money if they fail to meet their obligations. When choosing between different types of loans, it&#8217;s generally better to go for a lower interest rate rather than a higher repayment amount.</p>
<p>This is because the higher the rate, the greater the chance that you&#8217;ll end up defaulting on your loan.</p>
<p><strong>Are there any disadvantages to online car finance?</strong></p>
<p>As with any major financial decision, it is important to be aware of the potential risks and pitfalls of online car finance, and some of the main ones include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Ongoing financial obligation</li>
</ul>
<p>If you opt for online car finance, you&#8217;ll still need to continue paying the monthly instalments throughout the life of the loan, and this can be a heavy ongoing financial obligation. In addition, there&#8217;s a possibility that you could face a penalty fee if you miss a single instalment payment, so it is crucial that you never take out more than you can afford to pay back.</p>
<ul>
<li>You have to pay even if you sell the car</li>
</ul>
<p>When you use online car finance, you will always have to make monthly payments, regardless of whether you sell the vehicle or not, and this can be frustrating if the car breaks down and becomes unusable, or you are forced to sell for another reason. You will still be required to clear the balance completely, whether the car is yours or not, and this can make it tricky if you need to buy another car.</p>
<ul>
<li>It can be difficult to get approved for a personal guarantee</li>
</ul>
<p>A personal guarantee is essentially a promise that you&#8217;ll repay the loan if you fail to meet your obligations, and this can be tricky to secure, especially when the financial climate is uncertain. This can make it tricky to get the loan you need.</p>
<ul>
<li>You will likely need to pass a credit check</li>
</ul>
<p>Even though many lenders offer personal guarantees, they may still require you to pass a credit check before approving you for one. This is because a personal guarantee is often used by companies who want to ensure that they&#8217;re dealing with someone who has a good credit history and isn&#8217;t likely to default on their loan.</p>
<p><strong>The bottom line</strong></p>
<p>Online car finance offers a convenient way to purchase a new car without needing to visit lots of dealerships, but it comes at a cost. While it can help you save time and money, it also carries its own set of risks and disadvantages, so it&#8217;s vital that you understand what these are before making an informed choice. Once you have all the information, you can move forward to purchase your dream car.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/how-does-online-car-finance-work/">How does online car finance work?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Does car finance affect getting a mortgage in the UK?</title>
		<link>https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/does-car-finance-affect-getting-a-mortgage-in-the-uk/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlie Clayton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 09:35:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/?p=5951</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>When you think about buying a new home, you will likely need to take out a mortgage to be able to pay for it. This form of lending can allow you to pay back the price of the property over time. No matter what type of mortgage you opt for, the lenders are going to [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/does-car-finance-affect-getting-a-mortgage-in-the-uk/">Does car finance affect getting a mortgage in the UK?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When you think about buying a new home, you will likely need to take out a mortgage to be able to pay for it. This form of lending can allow you to pay back the price of the property over time.</p>
<p>No matter what type of mortgage you opt for, the lenders are going to look into your background and decide whether or not you will be able to eventually pay back the money you owe.</p>
<p>Now, if you have taken out a car finance loan, or have other debts in general, you may be wondering whether you will still be able to take out a UK mortgage. After all, a lot of debt can be an intimidating thing. But that’s what we are going to find out below!</p>
<p><strong>Why will lenders look into my background for a mortgage? </strong></p>
<p>If you are looking around for a home, it’s very likely that you will not be able to afford it immediately. That’s why you may look into taking out a mortgage. A mortgage is defined as an agreement made between you and a lender. The lender will have the right to repossess the property if you do not pay back the mortgage with added interest.</p>
<p>When you take out a loan with a lender, you will find that they will look into your background to see if you have any <a href="https://www.citizensadvice.org.uk/debt-and-money/help-with-debt/dealing-with-your-debts/making-a-plan-to-pay-your-debts/">unpaid debts</a>, or potentially any previous financial problems with other lenders.</p>
<p>Your financial situation is extremely important when it comes to taking out loans. The lender will look into the level of debts you have and what your monthly outgoings tend to be. This will ultimately affect how much money they will be willing to lend you, so that they can be confident you will be able to afford your mortgage.</p>
<p><strong>Will car finance affect my mortgage? </strong></p>
<p>If you have taken out a car finance deal, it will affect any mortgage that you take out in the UK. All lenders and banks are legally obligated to look at your finances before they offer any money for your mortgage. However, they will check more than just your car finance. They will also look at your:</p>
<ul>
<li>Job status</li>
<li><a href="https://www.hsbc.co.uk/credit-cards/how-to-improve-your-credit-score/">Credit rating</a></li>
<li>Loan repayment history</li>
<li>Previous loans and debt</li>
</ul>
<p>As car finance counts as a form of debt, it is a legal requirement for lenders and banks to check how much you have paid off, as well as how much you have taken out to afford any car payments. Ultimately, if they find that you have a large debt caused by your car finance, it’s very likely that they will only offer you a small loan to help you afford your mortgage. However, do not be completely put off of <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/bad-credit-car-finance/">car finance if you have a bad credit score</a>, as there are still solutions to this.</p>
<p><strong>Can I afford a mortgage and car finance loan together? </strong></p>
<p>Yes, you can apply for both mortgages and car finance, but it may not be the best idea. You may not be offered a mortgage if it can be proven that you can’t pay back the loan you have currently taken out. This doesn’t just have to be due to an unpaid debt from car finance. In fact, it could be any other type of monthly payment that could get you a refusal.</p>
<p>You need to examine your financial history and current payment schemes to see if you are eligible for a loan. If your monthly outgoings seem to be higher, the lender may see you as far too risky to offer a loan to. Therefore, they may refuse you entirely and you will not be able to receive a mortgage.</p>
<p><strong>What should I do before I take out a mortgage? </strong></p>
<p>The most important thing you can do is check your credit rating before you think of taking out a mortgage. If you have a bad credit rating, or a history of bankruptcy or an inability to pay back debts, you may find that your credit score is very low.</p>
<p>Make sure that you do not take out a loan of <em>any </em>kind – whether a mortgage or car finance – unless you know that you can pay it back. Honestly, if you do end up being able to take out a mortgage with your poor finance history, you may find that you will need to pay back a higher level of interest.</p>
<p>If you want to <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/3-simple-ways-to-increase-your-credit-score/">improve your credit rating</a>, make sure to repay all of your loans on time. You can do this by making small payments throughout the year to improve your line of credit. This includes any car finances or loans that you take out. The more credit you build up, the more likely it is that you will receive a mortgage from your lender or bank.</p>
<p>Would you like to see what your chances are of obtaining car finance? We have a handy <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/car-finance-calculator/">online car finance calculator</a> to help you make sense of the numbers – or you could simply <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/apply/">apply online now for a free and no-obligation quote</a> for car finance.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/does-car-finance-affect-getting-a-mortgage-in-the-uk/">Does car finance affect getting a mortgage in the UK?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why can’t I get finance for a car?</title>
		<link>https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/why-cant-i-get-finance-for-a-car/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlie Clayton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 08:59:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/?p=5948</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Whether you are buying your first car or you are looking for a new model as an upgrade on your existing one, it can take a lot of money to obtain the vehicle of your dreams. Not everyone is lucky enough to have the money readily available for them to buy a car straight away. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/why-cant-i-get-finance-for-a-car/">Why can’t I get finance for a car?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Whether you are buying your first car or you are looking for a new model as an upgrade on your existing one, it can take a lot of money to obtain the vehicle of your dreams. Not everyone is lucky enough to have the money readily available for them to buy a car straight away. In fact, great numbers of people will need to take out a loan in order to finance their car.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, there are many reasons why you may not be eligible for finance to help you afford a car. Here are some examples of why you might be rejected for this type of car loan.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>You have a poor credit rating</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>One of the main reasons why you may get rejected for a car finance deal is poor credit. When you try to buy an expensive item on finance, your bank or lender will need to take a look at your credit rating to see if you are worth the risk. If you are deemed as a bigger risk, it’s very likely that you will be rejected for a loan, or you may be offered a loan with a higher interest rate.</p>
<p>Your credit rating can be lowered if you have additional debts, missed payments or loans that you need to pay back. However, the opposite can also apply. If you have no debts, and you do not have enough evidence to show that you are trustworthy enough to pay back your loan, you may not even receive a <a href="https://www.barclaycard.co.uk/personal/money-matters/credit-score-basics/how-can-i-raise-my-credit-rating-even-further">credit rating</a>. This would mean you cannot generate a score that shows you can pay back what you owe. As a result, you could be rejected for car finance.</p>
<ol start="2">
<li><strong>Age &amp; youth</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>Although this may make you feel as if you are being discriminated against, unfortunately, lenders do tend to favour older drivers when it comes to taking out financial loans.</p>
<p>Finance agreements can only be taken out by people who are over the age of 18. However, if you fall between 18-21, there’s a chance that your age may be a deciding factor about whether or not you will be offered a loan.</p>
<p>Don’t be too downhearted about this type of rejection. There will almost certainly be other lenders who would be willing to provide you with a loan.</p>
<ol start="3">
<li><strong>Employability</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>When you go to each lender, you may find that they have wide-ranging criteria you need to fulfil in order to achieve the loan.</p>
<p>Essentially, the lender needs to make sure you are not a liability when it comes to paying back your debts. Therefore, if you do not have a job, are <a href="https://www.gov.uk/working-for-yourself">self-employed</a> or have just started a brand-new job, you may find that your application for a loan is rejected.</p>
<ol start="4">
<li><strong>Income</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>The lender is going to look at your financial history before they decide whether or not they will accept your loan request. This will include your wage and outgoings. If they deem that you cannot pay back your loan, or you do not have enough money to do so, you may be rejected.</p>
<p>Are you ready to discover just how good a car finance deal you could obtain with our help? If so, <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/apply/">simply apply today</a>; we can give you a free no-obligation quote, drawing upon our panel of lenders, so that you can be surer about your options for a car loan.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/why-cant-i-get-finance-for-a-car/">Why can’t I get finance for a car?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The best cities for students to drive in</title>
		<link>https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/the-best-cities-for-students-to-drive-in/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlie Clayton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2022 12:22:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/?p=5850</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Ah, our student days; the team here at Car Finance Genie remembers them well. But to adopt a more serious tone for a second, the question of which cities are best for student driving is a very interesting and relevant one. After all, you may be a teenager in the process right now of deciding [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/the-best-cities-for-students-to-drive-in/">The best cities for students to drive in</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ah, our student days; the team here at Car Finance Genie remembers them well. But to adopt a more serious tone for a second, the question of which cities are best for student driving is a very interesting and relevant one.</p>
<p>After all, you may be a teenager in the process right now of deciding on universities to apply for, or someone slightly older, contemplating the challenge of taking on a degree course for what might be the first time in your life. And you <em>might </em>happen to drive, whether because you have to do so, or because you simply wish to make the most of your student days on four wheels.</p>
<p>In many ways, the question of which cities are the best for students to drive in, is the same as the question of what cities are best for <em>anyone </em>to drive in.</p>
<p>Students are like any other group of people in that they might use their cars to fulfil ‘essential’ duties like the weekly shop or heading home to their parents from time to time. Or they might do a fair amount of more ‘recreational’ driving, such as taking inebriated friends to and from the club or embarking on road trips.</p>
<p>Whatever the situation may be for you, if you are a student – whether would-be or current, and regardless of age – you might appreciate some ‘cut out and keep’ advice on which cities are most ideal for those driving during their time at university or college.</p>
<p>It’s a subjective question to attempt to answer, of course. So, we decided to come up with a rundown of relatively ‘student-driver-friendly’ cities, while throwing in titbits of research findings that could be of interest to you.</p>
<p><strong>Birmingham </strong></p>
<p>While – when we ‘oldies’ are put in mind of Birmingham driving – we may immediately think of the likes of the Birmingham Superprix, the Spaghetti Junction, and Nigel Mansell, for today’s students, it’s likely to be the pleasure and convenience of the driving experience that largely defines the city for them.</p>
<p>Yes, that’s right; according to research put together by the car parts firm Mister Auto, and <a href="https://inews.co.uk/essentials/lifestyle/cars/car-news/these-are-the-uks-best-and-worst-cities-for-drivers-362511">reported on by the <em>i </em>newspaper</a>, Birmingham ranked first in the UK as a city for drivers.</p>
<p>The company devised its rankings of various cities around the world by taking into account such factors as the given city’s driving infrastructure, safety, and the costs of parking, petrol and road tax. Scores were then given for those factors.</p>
<p>With this methodology applied, Birmingham was positioned first in the UK, and 27<sup>th</sup> in the broader study of 100 shortlisted cities, with an overall score of 90.63 out of a possible 100.</p>
<p>It wasn’t all good news for Birmingham, though, as the same study also found it to be the worst in the UK for pollution. On that score, it will be interesting to see what longer-term impact the Clean Air Zone – introduced last summer – has on efforts to drive down pollution in the city.</p>
<p>The West Midlands city is home to no fewer than five universities – namely the University of Birmingham, Aston University, Birmingham City University, University College Birmingham, and Newman University. So, whatever you make of Birmingham’s roads, you can be sure of an active and rewarding student life here.</p>
<p><strong>York </strong></p>
<p>The historic county town of Yorkshire is a fun and enchanting place to be a student on a number of levels. This beautiful city is something of a tourist epicentre in North Yorkshire, thanks in large part to stunning historic architecture and cultural attractions ranging from York Minster and York Castle to York Theatre Royal and York Art Gallery.</p>
<p>But how does it fare specifically as a place for students to drive? The answer is: quite well, actually. Recent statistics have associated the city with much lower parking permit costs than other parts of the UK, as well as relatively cheap average car insurance quotes, and a manageable level of road traffic.</p>
<p>Plus, with this being “God’s Own County” of Yorkshire, you’ve always got the option of taking to the well-developed surrounding road network and exploring the many more distant pleasures of the region.</p>
<p><strong>Bournemouth </strong></p>
<p>It’s a part of the UK with a perhaps unwarranted ‘sleepy’ reputation – <a href="https://www.bournemouthecho.co.uk/news/18888346.bournemouth-uks-tired-town-according-kally-sleeps/">even if some reports suggest it is quite literally so</a>. But on the subject of the driving experience, it seems that the statistics say almost entirely good things about Bournemouth.</p>
<p>One can easily overlook the coastal resort town’s credentials as a destination for students; both Bournemouth University and Arts University Bournemouth carry its name, although they are both technically located across the border in nearby Poole. Distinguished alumni of the latter include such distinguished arts figures as <em>Slumdog Millionaire</em> screenwriter Simon Beaufoy, and the Turner Prize-winning photographer Wolfgang Tillmans.</p>
<p>A host of data suggest that Bournemouth is a pretty decent place for students to drive; it has been found to have a lower average university parking permit cost than a lot of other places in the UK, as well as very few instances of cars being clamped.</p>
<p>And there’s further good news if you are planning to spend some of your time as a Bournemouth-based student learning to drive; the international drivers’ education company Zutobi recently declared the South West England town <a href="https://zutobi.com/uk/driving-guides/best-cities-for-learner-drivers">the second best city in the UK for learner drivers</a>.</p>
<p>The firm reached this conclusion on the basis of a high overall pass rate compared to other areas of the country, as well as the safety of its roads, a mere 50 accidents being recorded per 100,000 people. That makes for a much less scary driving experience as a student than you would likely have in, say, Northampton, which saw 496 accidents per 100,000 people.</p>
<p><strong>Calgary, Canada </strong></p>
<p>Just in case you were tempted to think we were only going to cover UK cities in this rundown, we thought we’d throw in this option you might not have considered! We are including it here on the strength of its remarkable performance in the aforementioned Mister Auto study, it being the only one of the 100 global cities scrutinised in the research to manage a ‘perfect’ 100 score overall.</p>
<p>Presuming you are reading this as someone in the UK, if you do have the luxury of studying abroad, you could do a lot worse than choosing to go to university in this city in the western Canadian province of Alberta.</p>
<p>Not only is Calgary a <a href="https://yocket.com/blog/colleges-in-calgary">highly cosmopolitan place with plenty for its students to do both at and away from campus</a>, but its universities – including the likes of the University of Calgary and Mount Royal University – are internationally noted for their excellence. Oh, and the city also has a thriving and varied economy, with plenty of corporate head offices situated around the Calgary Metropolitan Region, so you might even fancy your chances of enjoying a rewarding career here after graduation.</p>
<p>But what about the driving experience, specifically? Well, Calgary racked up some seriously formidable scores out of 100 in the Mister Auto research, including a ‘daily average congestion score’ of 98.78, a ‘cost of parking by affordability score’ of 97.17, and a perfect 100 ‘city speed sample score’. The latter refers to the average speed motorists reach while driving in the city centre, expressed as a score.</p>
<p><strong>Glasgow </strong></p>
<p>Heading back to the UK, we just <em>had </em>to work in a Scottish city somewhere in this article, and we can’t think of a more suitable choice than Glasgow.</p>
<p>With the city situated on the River Clyde in the Scottish Lowlands being the most populous city in Scotland and indeed, one of the most populous in the entire United Kingdom, it should be no great surprise that Glasgow boasts a stunning complement of university-level institutions.</p>
<p>The likes of the University of Glasgow, the University of Strathclyde, and the Glasgow School of Art are all to be found here. But <a href="https://www.ucas.com/study-in/study-glasgow">as this UCAS guide sets out</a>, if you do become a student here, it’s probable that you will also become an aficionado of Irn-Bru, or caught up in the passion of the legendary ‘Old Firm’ footballing rivalry of Celtic vs Rangers.</p>
<p>Our greatest motivation for having Glasgow in our rundown, however, was probably its strong showing in the Mister Auto study we have already mentioned a few times in this blog post. With its overall score of 89.67 out of 100, Glasgow ranked 30<sup>th</sup> in the list of 100 shortlisted global cities competing to be considered the best ones to drive in, which was enough to make it the second best in the UK (behind Birmingham).</p>
<p>Glasgow fared well in the study for such aspects as congestion levels, the speeds that people drive at in the city centre, and the affordability of petrol. So, if you intend to do a decent amount of driving during your time as a student in Scotland, choosing to study in this enchanting historical city could be one of the best decisions you make.</p>
<p><strong>Manchester </strong></p>
<p>Is the North West England city the very <em>best </em>place overall to drive as a student in the UK? The short answer is: probably not. After all, in the Mister Auto study, it did manage ‘only’ sixth place among the UK’s top cities for drivers, and 44<sup>th</sup> among the 100 shortlisted locations around the world.</p>
<p>So, why are we including it in our list? Well, it seems that a major strength of Manchester as a destination for student motorists is its cheap petrol prices compared to many other parts of the country. Sure enough, Mister Auto gave the city a 95.30 out of 100 ‘cost of petrol by affordability score’, although the research also found that drivers here benefitted from manageable congestion levels and fairly affordable parking.</p>
<p>However, there’s also a much bigger picture to consider with Manchester, including the hugely satisfying all-round student life that could await you if you enrol at one of its well-regarded higher-education institutions such as the University of Manchester or Manchester Metropolitan University.</p>
<p>Manchester is an immensely diverse and welcoming city, with a little something for everyone. It is particularly noted for having one of the most exciting nightlife scenes of any UK city outside London, with Canal Street a renowned focus for LGBT revellers.</p>
<p>The city also boasts one of Europe’s largest Chinatowns, and of course, it is home to Manchesters City and United – two of England’s most successful football clubs. When these factors are considered alongside a <a href="https://www.manchester.ac.uk/study/experience/student-life/living-costs/">highly affordable general cost of living</a>, you can probably see why so many student motorists are ‘driven’ to what Manchester represents.</p>
<p>And while we’re on the subject of affordability, are you finding it tricky to stretch to the cost of a car here? In that case, you might wish to talk to the Car Finance Genie team about the many attractive <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/manchester/">car finance options in Manchester</a> that we make available, even for those with less-than-immaculate credit histories.</p>
<p><strong>Finally, what are the <em>worst </em>places to drive as a student? </strong></p>
<p>Well, it might not shock you to hear that <strong>London</strong> doesn’t fare massively strongly in surveys like the ones we have referenced in this article. The Mister Auto study discovered that the city ranked as the country’s worst for congestion, average speed, and parking costs. But on the brighter side, the UK capital fared better for such things as air quality and facilities per capita.</p>
<p>And anyone who has ever tried to drive around <strong>Edinburgh</strong> – student or not – can probably understand why the data indicates it is the likeliest place in the country for drivers to get involved in a road-rage incident.</p>
<p>Or perhaps it would be a fairer statement to say – <a href="https://www.tripadvisor.co.uk/ShowTopic-g186525-i108-k10598602-First_Time_Driving_in_Edinburgh_Any_Tips_except_don_t-Edinburgh_Scotland.html">in the words of one Tripadvisor forum commenter a few years back</a> – “driving in Edinburgh is not difficult, parking in Edinburgh is difficult”? Regardless, the Scottish capital ranked only 68<sup>th</sup> out of the 100 shortlisted cities featured in Mister Auto’s research.</p>
<p>We’ll leave you to discuss that one with friends. But in the meantime, you will hopefully have acquired a bit of knowledge from the above that will guide you in your decisions about where in the UK – or even outside of the UK – to study, if you intend to do a decent amount of driving during your time at university.</p>
<p>Stay safe, and be sure to <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/">consider Car Finance Genie</a> if you find yourself in need of an affordable car finance deal while you are a student.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/the-best-cities-for-students-to-drive-in/">The best cities for students to drive in</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Buying a car from a dealer: everything you need to know</title>
		<link>https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/buying-a-car-from-a-dealer-everything-you-need-to-know/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Charlie Clayton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 12:19:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/?p=5843</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The mere prospect of buying a car – whether new or used – can conjure up very different feelings and associations in different people. For some of us, it can be a very exciting prospect – you might have long been eager to upgrade that unreliable ‘old banger’ to something new and a bit more [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/buying-a-car-from-a-dealer-everything-you-need-to-know/">Buying a car from a dealer: everything you need to know</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The mere prospect of buying a car – whether new or used – can conjure up very different feelings and associations in different people. For some of us, it can be a very exciting prospect – you might have long been eager to upgrade that unreliable ‘old banger’ to something new and a bit more desirable and glamorous. But for other people, the whole ‘world’ of car purchasing can be an overwhelming and intimidating one.</p>
<p>And of course, it’s not as if a dealer is the <em>only </em>place you could conceivably buy your next vehicle from. You could also purchase your next car privately, of course, but today, there are also options like car ‘supermarkets’ and brokers.</p>
<p>Anyway, <a href="https://www.which.co.uk/reviews/new-and-used-cars/article/where-to-buy-a-car-aEVpN2l7vgvV">there’s a whole separate debate about that</a>; for <em>this </em>blog post, we’re focusing specifically on the task of buying an automobile from a dealer. This one’s a long read, so feel free to make a coffee and settle down on the sofa for this run-through of our favourite tips for dealing with… erm, dealers when you are on the lookout for a new vehicle.</p>
<p><strong>Should I buy used or new? </strong></p>
<p>Before we get onto the ‘nitty gritty’ of deciding what you want from your next car, or the specifics of approaching a car dealer, it’s worth asking this somewhat broader question: would I be better off purchasing a used car for my next vehicle, or a showroom-sparkly-new model?</p>
<p><a href="https://www.whatcar.com/advice/buying/should-i-buy-a-new-nearly-new-or-used-car/n1107">As this guide on the subject from <em>What Car? </em>explains</a>, three in every four cars sold in the UK is typically a used one – but that doesn’t <em>automatically</em> translate into a used car being the best option for you.</p>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class=" wp-image-5848 aligncenter" src="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/app/uploads/2022/05/pexels-david-mcbee-395537-300x169.jpg" alt="" width="440" height="248"></p>
<p>Now, if the car that you want would cost way beyond your budget if bought new, you might feel that the decision to buy used has already been made for you. And even if you have a fair amount more financial ‘wiggle room’, looking to the used-car market could be a good first port of call, given that it really will give you an exceedingly broad range of car manufacturers and models to choose from.</p>
<p>Plus, if you like the idea of benefitting from the lower cost of a used car versus a new one, there are plenty of <a href="https://www.whatcar.com/news/used-car-of-the-year-awards-2022-approved-used-car-schemes/n23544">manufacturer-approved used schemes</a> that will help give you the utmost peace of mind about the reputability of who you are buying from.</p>
<p>And what’s the benefit of buying a new car? Well, you will get to choose a car in the exact specification that you desire, and will also have a full manufacturer warranty to protect you against the worst that could happen with your purchase. And you won’t have to worry about the history of the car you’re buying, either.</p>
<p>As always with questions like this, you will need to think carefully about what <em>your </em>priorities and circumstances are, in terms of matters like price and specification requirements. There is no entirely ‘risk-free’ route here, but whether you buy new, used or nearly new, there are respective ‘pros and cons’ to think about.</p>
<p><strong>Do you know what you want from your next car? </strong></p>
<p>The adage “knowledge is power” is applicable to a <em>lot </em>of things, and the process of buying a car is most certainly one of those things.</p>
<p>Now, we aren’t going to admonish you if you don’t have an exact make and model in mind already, although if you do, that will be great for focusing your search for the perfect example of your dream vehicle. It helps, though, to have at least some ideas for what you want in your next car, which will doubtless be informed by the reasons you are looking to buy a car in the first place.</p>
<p>Are you, for instance, seeking out a car because you are about to welcome a new addition to the family, and therefore need something reasonably priced, economical to run, practical and reliable to carry them around in? Or maybe you’ve just passed your driving test, or have just received a pay rise and have your eye on a bit of a ‘dream’ car such as a sporty coupe or cabriolet?</p>
<p>With so many car body styles out there – encompassing everything from humble city cars and superminis to MPVs, saloons and SUVs – you might have a lot of narrowing down to do when perusing the possibilities.</p>
<p>As for if you have a few models in mind already, a quick Google search for the reviews of those cars on sites like <a href="https://www.whatcar.com/reviews"><em>What Car?</em></a>, <a href="https://www.autocar.co.uk/car-reviews"><em>Autocar</em></a> and <a href="https://www.autoexpress.co.uk/car-reviews"><em>Auto Express</em></a> will enable you to get a better idea of their reputation.</p>
<p><strong>How much can I afford to spend on a new or used car? </strong></p>
<p>A really crucial factor all by itself, of course, will be your budget. Once you have at least a <em>vague </em>idea of what you will be looking for on your visit to the dealership, you will need to decide on a budget, and stick to it. This, in turn, will enable you to filter out some of the vehicles you had considered at the aforementioned stage.</p>
<p>When you are determining your budget for a car, it’s not just the headline price of a vehicle that you will need to think about. That’s because you should also very much account for the <em>ongoing </em>expenses associated with whatever models you are considering, on the basis that getting behind the wheel of your ‘dream’ vehicle won’t count for much if you can barely afford the fuel, road tax and insurance payments from one month to the next.</p>
<p>Don’t forget too, though, that you don’t necessarily have to fork out the entire price of a car upfront from whatever is presently sitting in your bank account. In fact, even many people who theoretically <em>could </em>pay for a vehicle upfront, instead take out a car finance agreement, because of how it allows them to spread the costs over a longer period of time and even <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/how-to-improve-your-credit-score-in-2022/">improve their credit score</a>.</p>
<p>Now, we know what some of you reading this are thinking: “I can’t take out a car finance deal! I’ve got a dodgy credit history, lenders will never accept me.” Well, that might not be quite true.</p>
<p>Here at Car Finance Genie, for instance, we have a proud track record of helping many people with less-than-perfect-credit scores get accepted for car finance. We offer attractive <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/bad-credit-car-finance/">bad-credit car finance options</a> for those who might be worrying about whether they can stretch to a car purchase at all.</p>
<p><strong>How to find the most suitable car dealer </strong></p>
<p>If, at this stage of reading, you’re thinking, “but we haven’t even approached a dealer yet!”, there’s a good reason we’ve structured this article that way; it really is the case that you need to do your research and establish what you’re interested in from a car, before you even walk into a dealership.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="wp-image-5846 aligncenter" src="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/app/uploads/2022/05/pexels-gustavo-fring-4173189-300x200.jpg" alt="" width="412" height="274"></p>
<p>But once you <em>have </em>accomplished the above things, it will be time to start your search for potential dealers. And with this being the 2020s, almost any car dealer worth bothering with will have a fairly well-developed online presence these days, so you should be able to start identifying dealers to potentially approach, and cars to look at, from the comfort of your own home.</p>
<p>Even here on the Car Finance Genie website, you can have a sift through <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/vehicle-stock/">some of the car models we presently make available for sale</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.citizensadvice.org.uk/consumer/buying-or-repairing-a-car/buying-a-used-car/">As Citizens Advice points out, though</a>, whatever business selling cars you might be tempted to approach, it is also important to establish the reputability of that business. That should mean doing your research to get a sense of the dealer’s general reputation, as well as looking for the sign of a trade association such as the Retail Motor Industry Federation.</p>
<p>If the thought of having to carry out research into each and every dealer you might consider fills you with tedium – or even if you might lack the time to do it – there’s always another option: using a broker.</p>
<p>The idea of using a broker is that you tell them what car you want, and they will then do the hard work of going off and buying it for you, so that you don’t have to engage directly with a dealer at all. You will, of course, still have to research the reputation of the broker itself before approaching them, but it could be an option if you aren’t confident about handling a dealer ‘in person’ when it comes to such things as haggling.</p>
<p>Another type of broker to consider is a car finance broker like ourselves here at Car Finance Genie. We may do car finance above all else, but we also have connections with carefully vetted and trusted dealers, so that <a href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/how-it-works/">you won’t even have to worry about comparing different dealers</a> once you have been approved for car finance through us.</p>
<p><strong>When is the right time to turn up at a car dealership? </strong></p>
<p>Let’s face it – even if you have settled on a dealer or two that you are confident in the reputability of, such as a manufacturer-approved one or an independent dealer that has strong reviews among locals, it can still be a bit scary to actually walk into such a place.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="wp-image-5847 aligncenter" src="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/app/uploads/2022/05/pexels-erik-mclean-6005585-300x200.jpg" alt="" width="362" height="241"></p>
<p>Still, there are certain things it is worth knowing in advance for your in-person visit to a dealership, or even just if you get on the phone to one.</p>
<p>There’s the matter of the <em>timing </em>of your visit, for example; as is the case with other firms that sell high-value products, dealers and their individual employees commonly have sales targets that they strive to meet, and these are often on a monthly or quarterly basis.</p>
<p>So, if you are eager to snap up a great deal, it could be a particularly good idea to turn up to the dealer towards the end of a month, particularly if that month is March, June, September or December. Think, too, about when particular types of cars are in most demand; you might have a hard time getting an attractive deal on a cabriolet during August when it’s sunny outside, but you will probably have much better luck if you attempt to do so during a drizzly December.</p>
<p>Another potentially excellent reason to approach a dealer in December is because many people focus on Christmas spending at this time of year rather than buying a new car, so dealers often see slow business during this part of the winter.</p>
<p><strong>The art of haggling is an art everyone can practise </strong></p>
<p>Speaking of getting a great deal on a car, it’s difficult for us to talk about it without touching on the subject of haggling.</p>
<p>In fact, there’s a whole art to haggling, and yes, you might be intimidated by the prospect of trying to ‘drive a hard bargain’ with an experienced dealer, but look at it this way: what do you have to lose? The realistic ‘worst-case’ scenario if you try to haggle is that the dealer might stand firm, and you simply have to decide whether you are happy to pay the asking price.</p>
<p>And if you <em>aren’t</em> happy, you always have the option of just walking away, or (if your circumstances and need for a car allow it) perhaps getting back in touch with the dealer at a time when they might be likelier to agree to a discount.</p>
<p>The MoneyHelper website <a href="https://www.moneyhelper.org.uk/en/everyday-money/buying-and-running-a-car/how-to-negotiate-when-buying-a-car">has some more in-depth advice on how to haggle successfully for a car</a>, including being friendly and polite, but also not telling the salesperson what your top limit is.</p>
<p>Even if your attempt to get a discount isn’t proving very successful, but you want the car enough, you could always say that you’re prepared to buy right there and then, as long as the two of you can agree on a price. This alone might be enough to get the dealer to finally budge on what they’re asking.</p>
<p><strong>Finally… don’t forget to scrutinise the car itself! </strong></p>
<p>It might seem like ‘common sense’ to some of our more experienced readers, but we can’t end this comprehensive guide without also touching on the things you need to check about the specific car you’re considering, <em>before </em>you commit to a purchase.</p>
<p>That will include such things as the car’s mileage, its MOT and service history, and whether the vehicle comes with a V5C (generally speaking, you are advised to avoid buying a vehicle that <em>doesn’t </em>have a V5C, otherwise often referred to as the ‘logbook’).</p>
<p>And if you <em>are </em>stood in front of the actual car on a dealer forecourt, you have an obvious opportunity to <a href="https://www.autoexpress.co.uk/car-news/used-car-guide/66420/used-car-checklist-what-to-look-for-when-buying-a-second-hand-car">carry out a visual inspection of the car</a>, and to ask for a test drive – the latter giving you the chance to listen for any worrying noises, such as a loud exhaust or squealing brakes.</p>
<p><strong>That’s the advice done – it’s time to get on with your search! </strong></p>
<p>There you have it – a top-to-bottom guide to the various key things you need to know about if you do decide to buy your next car from a dealer.</p>
<p>It doesn’t have to be <em>quite </em>as intimidating a process as you might imagine it to be, and equipping yourself with the knowledge you will have hopefully acquired from reading this, will help maximise your chances of landing the right vehicle for the right price. Good luck!</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk/buying-a-car-from-a-dealer-everything-you-need-to-know/">Buying a car from a dealer: everything you need to know</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://carfinancegenie.co.uk">Car Finance Genie</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
